Guide to the Tamiment Library Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Collection TAM.507
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.), 2007-present
  - Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers International Union (BCTGM), Dec 2009-present
    The Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers' International Union (BCTGM) is a labor union in the United States and Canada with a membership of 100,000. The union includes workers in bakeries, candy, cereal, sugar, grain mills, tobacco plants, food processing and manufacturing facilities and other related occupations related to these industries. The union traces its history to the founding of the Journeymen Bakers Union in 1886. The contemporary BCTGM was formed in January, 1999 from the merger of the Bakery, Confectionery and Tobacco Workers' International Union and the American Federation of Grain Millers. The BCTGM is affiliated with the AFL-CIO, the Canadian Labour Congress and the International Union of Food Workers (IUF).
  - Bitch Magazine, Nov 2009-present
    B-Word Worldwide, affiliated with Bitch Media, is the nonprofit organization best known for publishing the magazine Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture. Bitch Media’s mission is to provide and encourage an engaged, thoughtful feminist response to mainstream media and popular culture. The magazine was launched in 1996 by Lisa Jervis, Benjamin Shaykin, and Andi Zeisler.
  - Black Workers for Justice, May 2011-present
    The Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ) is a mass activist workers organization. It includes socialists, radical working class and general members, who link the immediate struggles in the workplaces and communities to a long term transitional radical program for Black empowerment/self-determination, social justice and social transformation. BWFJ was founded in 1981. Its labor and political perspectives grow out of an analysis of the development of the U.S. national and global economy, the U.S. imperialist state, and the ongoing role of the U.S. South as a fundamental pillar of U.S imperialism.
  - Brandworkers International, May 2012-present
    Founded in 2007, Brandworkers is a New York City-based organization that works to protect and advance the rights of retail and food employees. By training workers in social change tools and facilitating member-led workplace justice campaigns, Brandworkers promotes employer compliance with the law and challenges corporate misconduct in the community. The website contains information on campaigns and programs, news, and blog posts.
  - Bread and Roses Cultural Project, Aug 2009
    Bread and Roses, part of the 1199SEIU, was founded in 1979, as a cultural resource for union members and students in New York City who would otherwise have little access to the arts. Bread and Roses established the only permanent union exhibition space in the nation, Gallery 1199, at the union’s New York City headquarters. Bread and Roses appears to be defunct as of 2009.
  - Bread and Roses Heritage Committee, Sep 2012-present
    Bread and Roses Heritage Committee is the organizing committee for the annual Bread and Roses Labor Day Festival in Lawrence, Massachusetts. The festival was created in honor of the Bread and Roses strike in 1912. The website contains a schedule of events, news, and Lawrence labor history.
  - Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers, Local 1, Dec 2012-present
    The International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 was granted a charter by the National Union of Bricklayers of the U.S.A. on October 17, 1868 in Brooklyn, New York and is one of the oldest continuously-existing locals in New York City. The union represents bricklayers, plasterers, stonesetters, and pointers, cleaners and caulkers. The website contains their newsletter, events, and news listings.
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen (BRS), Dec 2009-present
    The Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen, founded in 1901, represents nearly 9,500 signal employees on both the freight railroads and the passenger and commuter railroads across the United States and into Canada. The Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen is affiliated with the AFL-CIO and the Transportation Trades Department.
  - Building and Construction Trades Department, AFL-CIO, (BCTD), Oct 2012-present
    The Building and Construction Trades Department, AFL-CIO, (BCTD) is the coordinating body of construction unions in the AFL-CIO. The department provides training and support to construction workers. It is made up of seven committees: Apprenticeship and Training; the Canadian Executive Board; General Presidents' Committee on Contract Maintenance; Labor-Management Committee; Legislative Task Force Committee; National Organizing Committee; and the Women in the Trades Committee. The website contains news, directories, legislative issues, and field services.
  - Building Bridges Radio, Aug 2009-present
    Building Bridges: Your Community and Labor Report is a labor news web blog and a weekly one hour program covering local, national and international labor and community issues over radio WBAI-Pacifica 99.5 FM. Besides covering labor issues, the website focuses on human rights abuses, environmental concerns, US political domination abroad, and other social justice issues.
  - Building Trades Employers' Association of the City of New York, Feb 2009-present
    Building Trades Employers Association (BTEA) is affiliated with 28 trade union contractor associations, representing the 1,700 construction managers, general contractors and specialty subcontractor firms in New York City, who employ 125,000 people. Members range in size from multi-billion dollar internationally recognized firms to small and mid-sized specialty trade contracting firms. The BTEA promotes safety, skill training, professional standards, and works to strengthen the economic vitality and social fabric of New York City.
  - California Nurses Association/National Nurses Organizing Committee (CNA/NNOC), Dec 2009-Dec 2011
    Founded in 1903, the California Nurses Association, and its national arm, the National Nurses Organizing Committee is a labor organization of registered nurses and health care unions. CNA/NNOC has 86,000 members in 50 states, representing nurses at scores of hospitals, clinics, and home health agencies. Since 2000, over 19,000 RNs at 50 hospitals have elected to affiliate with CNA. CNA/NNOC is also a founding member of the 150,000-member National Nurses United.
  - Caucus of Rank-and-File Educators, Sep 2012-present
    The Caucus of Rank and File Educators (CORE) is a coalition within the Chicago Teacher’s Union that took power in the union in 2010. They are against school privatization and led the 2012 Chicago teacher’s strike. The website contains news updates and a newsletter.
  - Center for Labor Renewal, May 2011-present
    The Center for Labor Renewal, launched in 2006, is a think tank dedicated to combining different threads of working class organizing and activism to promote the transformation and renewal of labor as a progressive social movement in this country and internationally.
  - Center for Study of Working Class Life, May 2011-present
    The Center for Study of Working Class Life, founded by the faculty and staff at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, in November, 1999, explores the meaning of class in the present day. The center studies social questions, including the gap between the rich and the poor, the attack on government programs through privatization, and other questions. The Center studies class mainly with tools of the social sciences, but also uses the arts as a tool of study.
  - Change to Win, Dec 2009-present
    Change to Win Strategic Organizing Center is a coalition of American labor unions formed in 2005. The coalition currently consists of four member unions: The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT); Service Employees International Union (SEIU); United Farm Workers (UFW); and United Food and Commercial Workers (UFCW) and supports 5.5 million workers.
  - Chicago Teachers Union, Sep 2012-present
    The Chicago Teacher’s Union, chartered in 1937, represents 30,000 teachers and educational support personnel working in the Chicago Public Schools. The Chicago Teachers Union is an organization of educators dedicated to advancing and promoting quality public education, improving teaching and learning conditions, and protecting members' rights. They are affiliated with the Chicago Federation of Labor (CFL), the Illinois State Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (ISFL-CIO), the American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), the Illinois Federation of Teachers (IFT), and the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). The website contains news, events, and information on their 2012 strike.
  - Chinese Staff Workers Association, Sep 2007-present
    Chinese Staff & Workers' Association (CSWA) was formed in New York City in 1979, to support over 1,300 workers from various trades and ages, injured and non-injured, documented and undocumented workers. It primarily assists workers in restaurants, the garment and construction industries, although it is active among workers in a variety of professions. The organization serves workers from all backgrounds, most of its members are Chinese and most of its efforts directed at employers in Chinatown.
  - Civil Service Merit Council, Feb 2009-Mar 2009
    The Civil Service Merit Council, founded in 1971, is a non-partisan coalition of individuals and organizations whose primary purpose was to increase the level of efficiency and integrity of government. The Merit Councils primary objective is to ensure that all appointments to the New York civil service shall be made through competitive examinations to properly classified positions from among persons duly qualified without regard to race, religion, age, sex, or political opinion or affiliation. The Council is dedicated to preserving and advancing the rights and tenure of all persons in the Merit System.
  - Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375, DC 37, AFSCME - AFL-CIO, Sep 2007-present
    The Civil Service Technical Guild (Local 375, DC 37), founded in 1929, represents 7,000 engineers, architects, scientists, chemists, planners, and other technical inspectors working for the City of New York. The guild’s goals include the prevention of the outsourcing city contracts, fighting for the adherence to civil service laws, enforcing contracts, and fighting privatization. The union is affiliated with the ASFCME and the AFL-CIO.
  - Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, Sep 2007-present
    The Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU), founded in 1972, consists of members from seventy-seven international and national unions with fifty chapters across the country. It is the independent voice of black workers within the trade union movement, challenging organized labor to be more relevant to the needs and aspirations of black and poor workers.
  - Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions, Jul 2011-present
    The Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions was formed in 1992 to support the organization of new graduate employee unions; to strengthen established unions; and to provide a forum for graduate employee unionists to meet, share information and work together toward common goals. The coalition holds an annual conference featuring workshops on organizing, leadership development, negotiation strategies, and member mobilization. Each year, the conference is hosted by a different union; here are the locations and hosting unions (and international union affiliations) of the past ten conferences. This website is set up in a “wiki” format.
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women, Sep 2007-present
    Formed in 1974, Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW) is a nonpartisan organization whose primary mission is to unify all union women in a viable organization to determine our common problems and concerns and to develop action programs within the framework of our unions to deal effectively with our objectives. With members from 54 international and national unions across the U.S. and Canada, CLUW has a network of more than 40 chapters. CLUW is endorsed by the AFL-CIO and its international and national unions.
  - Committee for Free Trade Unionism, Sep 2009-present
    The Committee for Free Trade Unionism (CFTU), was founded in ca. 2008 by Thomas R. Donahue, President Emeritus of the AFL-CIO, and appears to be largely composed of individuals involved with the group Social Democrats USA. CFTU aims to promote trade union freedom by working with a worldwide network of trade union experts and other groups committed to the advancement of free trade unionism, galvanize the efforts of international labor, and providing defenses against trade union persecution and oppression anywhere in the world.
  - Communications Workers of America, Sep 2007-present
    Communications Workers of America (CWA), founded in 1947, is America's largest communications and media union, represents over 700,000 men and women in both private and public sectors, including over half a million workers who are employed in telecommunications, broadcasting, cable TV, journalism, publishing, electronics and general manufacturing, as well as airline customer service, government service, health care, education and other fields. The union includes some 1,200 chartered local unions across the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. Members live in approximately 10,000 communities, making CWA one of the most geographically diverse unions. CWA is headquartered in Washington, DC, and affiliated with the AFL-CIO, the Canadian Labour Congress, and Union Network International
  - Communications Workers of America, District 1, Sep 2007-present
    District 1 of the Communications Workers of America (CWA) includes 327 CWA local unions in New York, New Jersey, New England, and eastern Canada. Members are employed in many different sectors of the economy including, telecommunications; health care; higher education; manufacturing; broadcast and cable television; commercial printing and newspapers; state, local, and country government.
  - Communications Workers of America, District 2-13, Mar 2009-present
    District 2-13 is responsible for servicing all CWA locals in Pennsylvania, Maryland, Delaware, Virginia, West Virginia, and the District of Columbia. Members are employed in many different sectors of the economy including, telecommunications; health care; higher education; manufacturing; broadcast and cable television; commercial printing and newspapers; state, local, and country government.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1032, Feb 2009-present
    Communications Workers of America Local 1032 represents about 6,000 workers in a variety of professions and fields in several New Jersey State Departments, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, several New Jersey towns and counties as well as several private sector work sites.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1060, Nov 2012-present
    CWA Local 1060 represents workers at Lucent (formerly Bell Labs, in Murray Hill, NJ). The website contains information on benefits, minutes, financials, and news.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1101, Feb 2009-present
    mmunication Workers of America, Local 1103 is based in New York, New York.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1103, Mar 2009-present
    Communication Workers of America, Local 1103 is based in Port Chester, New York.
  - Communication Workers of America, Local 1109, Nov 2012-present
    The Communications Workers of America Local 1109 represents over 2,000 telecommunications technicians and customer service representatives in Brooklyn, New York. The website contains information on benefits, political action campaigns, their publication, the Wire, and news.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1150, Feb 2009-present
    Communication Workers of America, Local 1150 is based in New York, NY, and represents landline technicians in the New York and New Jersey metropolitan area.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1153, Feb 2009-present
    Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 was chartered in 1975, after more than 500 members of the Manhattan-based Local 1150 petitioned for a new local to represent American Telephone & Telegraph's Long Lines (long distance) employees working in the White Plains and Mount Kisco area. 1153 consists of three sections: Plant (construction and maintenance), Traffic (operators) and Administrative (clerical). Local 1153 advocates for many issues, including job losses, job pressures, seniority rights, the creation of new job titles, health and safety, and discrimination based on sex and race.
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1180, Sep 2007-present
    Local 1180 is an affiliate of the Communications Workers of America (CWA), representing over 8,000 workers in the New York City area. Members work in the public sector, but the union also represents workers at the Board of Education, the Housing Authority, the Transit Authority, the School Construction Authority, the state's Unified Court System; at private companies such as the Jacob Javits Convention Center; and at not-for-profit organizations including Planned Parenthood of New York City, the ASPCA, Human Rights First, and Human Rights Watch.
  - Cyberunions, Nov 2011-present
    Cyberunions, created by Walter Pantland, works to get trade unions to use technology to organize and building an open source labor movement. The site contains both theoretical pieces on and more practical resources for activists. The website also produces a podcast on trade unions, technology, and economics.
  - David Bacon Photographs and Stories, Sep 2007-present
    David Bacon is photojournalist, labor organizer, and immigrant-rights activist, and author. The website contains photographs and articles by Bacon.
  - District Council 1707, Nov 2012-present
    District Council 1707 of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) is the only council within AFSCME that is chartered exclusively to represent private, nonprofit employees. It currently represents about 25,000 workers throughout the New York City area (and New York State), including those within private sector fundraising and advocacy agencies, case work and group work agencies, teaching and related organizations, child care centers, home care services, and Head Start programs. The website contains information on the political action committee, class and workshops, benefits, and news.
  - Domestic Workers United, May 2011-present
    Initially founded in 2000 by the Women Workers Project of Committee of Against Anti-Asian Violence, the Domestic Workers United (DWU) is an organization of Caribbean, Latina and African nannies, housekeepers, and caregivers for the elderly in New York, organizing for fair labor standards and to help build a movement to end exploitation and oppression. DWU organizes workers from the Caribbean, Africa and Latin America, and coordinates with the other domestic workers organizations through the NY Domestic Workers Justice Coalition to build the power of the entire workforce.
  - Embedded With Organized Labor, Dec 2011-Dec 2012
    Embedded With Organized Labor is the labor blog by Steve Early. Steve Early is a labor journalist and lawyer who has written for numerous publications. He is the author of Embedded With Organized Labor: Journalistic Reflections on the Class War at Home and The Civil Wars in U.S. Labor. Early was a Boston-based international representative or organizer for the Communications Workers of America for 27 years, and is a member of the editorial advisory committees of three independent labor publications: Labor Notes, New Labor Forum and Working USA.
  - Employee Free Choice Act Now!, Dec 2008-Dec 2010
    The Employee Free Choice Act was a legislative bill that was introduced into both chambers of the U.S. Congress on March 10, 2009. The bill's purpose was to, “amend the National Labor Relations Act to establish an efficient system to enable employees to form, join, or assist labor organizations [unions], to provide for mandatory injunctions for unfair labor practices during organizing efforts, and for other purposes.” This website was a petition website in support of the act. The central part of the legislation would have provided for automatic certification of unions if a majority of potential members had signed unionization cards
  - Excluded Workers Congress, Oct 2011-present
    The Excluded Worker Congress consists of networks of organizations that represent a base of workers that are either by law or by practice excluded from the right to organize. The nine sectors of the Excluded Workers Congress include domestic workers, farm workers, taxi drivers, restaurant workers, day laborers, guest workers, workers from Southern right- to-work states, workfare workers and formerly incarcerated workers. They are a project of the Inter-Alliance Dialogue, an alliance of Grassroots Global Justice Alliance, Jobs with Justice, National Day Labor Organizing Network, National Domestic Worker Alliance, Pushback Network, and Right to the City Alliance and affiliated with the AFL-CIO and other unions.
  - Farm Labor Organizing Committee (FLOC), Dec 2009-present
    The Farm Labor Organizing Committee, AFL-CIO, (FLOC), founded in 1967, is a labor union representing migrant farm workers in the Midwestern United States and North Carolina.
  - Fruit of Labor Singing Ensemble, July 2012-present
    The Fruit of Labor Singing Ensemble is a labor affiliated singing group that grew out of the struggle of organizing African American workers in the “Black Belt” region of North Carolina and the South. Their music captures the working class’ history of community and workplace struggles. The website features their music and event listings.
  - Glass, Molders, Pottery, Plastics and Allied Workers International Union (GMP), Dec 2009-present
    The Glass, Molders, Pottery, Plastics & Allied Workers (GMP) International Union, with its origins dating back to 1842 represents thousands of workers in the glass, molders, plastics, pottery, cast metals, fiberglass, defense, fine china, glass and plastic containers, insulation and sanitary-ware industries as well as workers in government, healthcare and a variety of other industries. The GMP International Union currently belongs to the AFL-CIO, CLC and is active in the Union Label and Service Trades Department as well as the Maritime Trades Department.
  - Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC), UAW Local 2110, Jul 2011-present
    GSOC/UAW Local 2110 is the union of teaching, research and graduate assistants at New York University. As the chosen representative of the majority of NYU graduate employees, the Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC) is committed to restoring collective bargaining rights for our membership and forcing NYU to once again recognize our union, as it did when GSOC and NYU signed a contract governing graduate employment in 2002. Collective bargaining gives employees a say in their working conditions by empowering chosen representatives of those workers to negotiate with employers over issues like pay, workload protections, workplace safety and benefits.
  - Guerrilla News Network, Feb 2009-present
    Guerrilla News Network is an independent news organization with headquarters in New York City and production facilities in Berkeley, California. Their mission is to expose people to important global issues through cross-platform guerrilla programming.
  - Industrial Workers of the World, Feb 2007-present